<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-19T12:59:53+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nathan Masters</title><subtitle>Somewhere you can find out a little more about me and what I get up to.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Les Saints de Glace - is it real?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/19/Saints-des-glaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Les Saints de Glace - is it real?" /><published>2020-05-19T11:10:27+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T11:10:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/19/Saints-des-glaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/19/Saints-des-glaces.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;confinement-is-in-progress-and-so-is-this-website&quot;&gt;Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, as confinement dragged on over a couple of months here in Switzerland, and 
likewise it seems all over the rest of Europe, the weather was positively glorious! The skies were
big with dawn to dusk blue, while we were all cooped up in our homes with nowhere to go.
The view of our neighbours’ extensive balconies in the sun taunted us each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just as May was getting under way, and the summer felt like it was truly beginning to arrive,
there was a spot of cold weather. Rain came, and temperatures fell, and suddenly it was 
the beginning of spring again. “Well it’s to be expected, it’s Les Saints de Glace”, Camille
mentioned off hand as if it was something I really should have known about. The
idea that a brief drop in cold weather occurred annually with such regularity there were a 
group of saints collectively known as the Ice Saints, was pretty exciting. Perhaps, rather
naïvely I laughed off the suggestion that this was “a real thing”… Surely not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, much to her annoyance, I was soon explaining how so many of these phenomena are purely
coincidence, and subject to perception bias, etc., etc… Unsurprisingly, this didn’t ease 
any tensions. We changed the subject. If confinement in a studio flat has taught us anything,
it’s how to let sleeping dogs lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while those dogs slept quietly, plans were afoot. I was soon back at my laptop
utilising some of my new found Python knowledge, to see if I could provide at least a crumb
of empirical evidence against her, and seemingly centuries of tradition, that claimed a
wonderful meteorological phenomenon was occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it seems obtaining data of extensive meteorological measurements can be 
somewhat difficult - at least without paying the Swiss weather organisation, or any number
of other data resellers online. But, eventually, and with my eyes subconsciously glancing
over many obtrusive advertisements I was able to very slowly collect average daily temperatures
in May for the Geneva Airport. And, I was initially a little taken back…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/daily_temps.png&quot; alt=&quot;Daily Temperatures 2010-2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;
Average daily temperatures for each day in May at Geneva International Airport. Red line 
indicates the average over these ten years, with the ribbon indicating ± standard deviation.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Les Saints de Glace is a period in May, characterised by the saint days of four saints:
St. Mamertus, St. Pancras (of train station fame), St. Servatius, and sometimes St. Sophia
and St. Boniface of Tarsus. Typically, it is counted as the dates form the 11th to the 15th May,
when “Cold Sophie” (i.e. St. Sophia) arrives. And what’s this? For the past 10 years, it certainly 
seems like there is a big drop in temperatures with Les Saints de Glace. 
Were the Saints really bringing about some unseasonable weather? Was the unexpected drop
in temperatures entirely expected? Was I about to see myself sheepishly show Camille the
data and admit that I was wrong? Of course not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/weather.gif# right prop50&quot; alt=&quot;Daily Temperatures 1997-2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of advertisements selling useless products to my brain later, and I had data back
to 1997. Finally, the trend began to fall apart. Phew! That was close. Of course, all of
this is a little tongue in cheek. Presenting data from a single weather station, over a 
period of 23 years is hardly rigorously rejecting my null hypothesis, but it’s a start. In fact, the Swiss
Weather agency, MeteoSuisse, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meteosuisse.admin.ch/home/climat/climat-de-la-suisse/informations-saisonnieres/les-saints-de-glace.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;did investigate this&lt;/a&gt;. 
They found no more ground frosts during the Ice Saints period, than any other period in April
or May going back to 1965. And perhaps, more interestingly, point out that the dates of the 
Saints des Glaces have switched over the years. Prior to the shift to the Gregorian Calendar
in 1582, the dates would actually be the 19 - 23rd May. Unfortunately for 
Camille, there is no marked increase in frosts, nor a decrease in temperatures for this period
either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, there looks to be no direct evidence that the Saints des Glaces phenomena is real. 
Those pesky Ice Saints have no more effect on the weather on their special days than
any other saints. Skepticism of tradition has prevailed, and this blog article was written. 
Camille can be satisfied in the knowledge that from her experiential evidence of the last 
ten years, she was right to believe in this cold weather snap, and I can be quietly smug 
that I was right all along. Isn’t it wonderful when there’s a happy ending, and perhaps 
for now I’ll leave disproving fairies for another time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan</name></author><summary type="html">Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Bokeh: Direct Comparisons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/12/comparisons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Bokeh: Direct Comparisons" /><published>2020-05-12T13:24:27+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T13:24:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/12/comparisons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/12/comparisons.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;confinement-is-in-progress-and-so-is-this-website&quot;&gt;Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a quick post to present the direct comparison of cumulative deaths for a number of
countries. This data is accurate as of the 12th May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out Bokeh’s use of a dedicated Source Data Structure makes quick changes a little
difficult. Another thing I haven’t quite worked out is the scale of the x-axis…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These graphs use the easily available data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/download-todays-data-geographic-distribution-covid-19-cases-worldwide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/img/Bokeh/corona-comparisons.html&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-scripts&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; float=&quot;centre&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan</name></author><summary type="html">Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Bokeh: UK/Swiss Covid Comparisons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/11/interactive_bokeh.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Bokeh: UK/Swiss Covid Comparisons" /><published>2020-05-11T19:44:27+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-11T19:44:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/11/interactive_bokeh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/11/interactive_bokeh.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;confinement-is-in-progress-and-so-is-this-website&quot;&gt;Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An update from my previous post. My previous post presented some data compiled in Python
and using matplotlib to output a static post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve tried to see if I can present this data in a slightly more interactive way.
Along comes “Bokeh” to save the day - or at least help a little. A little fiddly to work out,
but not too tricky, it presents nice enough plots, which didn’t require too much new learning.
All the compilation into html is performed for you, and simple inclusion into R markdown script
means you can all see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently residing in Switzerland, and originally from the UK, it’s a little worrying to see
how the two countries outcomes are so different…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These graphs use the easily available data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/download-todays-data-geographic-distribution-covid-19-cases-worldwide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little difficulty I had in particular with Bokeh, was scaling the legend responsively with 
page width. So sorry if you’re looking at this on a small screen :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/img/Bokeh/UK-CH_corona.html&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-scripts&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; float=&quot;centre&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan</name></author><summary type="html">Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Covid Confinement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/welcome-to-confinement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Covid Confinement" /><published>2020-05-01T16:07:27+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T16:07:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/welcome-to-confinement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/welcome-to-confinement.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;confinement-is-in-progress-and-so-is-this-website&quot;&gt;Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been trying to understand Python a bit better with a few exercises. Previously
I’ve typically worked in R for data analysis and visualisation, but with the added time on my hands
I’ve had the opportunity to try and get to know another system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nice to have the opportunity to suddenly be given a huge amount of publicly available data,
and I’m sure like many people who are able to make their own plots and analyse the data, the 
temptation was there to make some comparisons. I was mainly inspired by the plots of the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/a26fbf7e-48f8-11ea-aeb3-955839e06441&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Financial Times&lt;/a&gt; created by 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jburnmurdoch&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@jburnmurdoch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here are some initial attempts to put together some plots using the easily available data
from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/download-todays-data-geographic-distribution-covid-19-cases-worldwide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Latest-Plot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Latest_Plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll have a look at how else I can begin to plot this data interactively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan</name></author><summary type="html">Confinement is in progress… and so is this website.</summary></entry></feed>